# Cameron H. Matthews

1046 Via Vera Cruz San Diego, CA 92078

(confidential)

cameron.matthews@koatechnologies.com

Phone: (760) 268-9082

# **Summary**

Technology executive with strong leadership ability, deep technical skills, and successful management skills who possesses over 30 years of cross-vertical security, software, and systems engineering experience. Security and technology pioneer in the areas of threat intelligence exchange, rapid vulnerability notification, and security situational awareness. Areas of expertise include:

- Secure software and systems engineering
- Secure Software Development Lifecycle execution and training
- Systems integration

- Risk and threat management
- Corporate security strategy creation
- Corporate security culture development

## **Professional Experience**

Nth Generation San Diego, CA Apr 2019 - Present vCISO | Sr. Security Consultant

- Leading organizations in creating or aligning a Corporate Security Program
  with a globally recognized cybersecurity framework such as the Center for
  Internet Security (CIS) Critical Security Controls (CSC), the NIST
  Cybersecurity Framework (CSF), and the NIST 800-171.
- Reducing a client's financial, legal, and reputational risk while increasing their cybersecurity posture and culture.
- Optimizing security operations, incorporating active threat intelligence and late-breaking vulnerability data, preventing data loss (especially missioncritical data or intellectual property), providing continual governance, and ensuring compliance with industry- or government-mandated rules and regulations.
- If the client already has a CISO, serve in an augmentation role to assist in building a corporate security team, translating business dictates into security operations directives, and fostering a corporate security culture.
- Create or optimize an existing Enterprise Security Architecture to enhances the business's ability to securely operate, resist hacker attacks and subversion, and scale to match C-level and Board intent.

**Koa Technologies** San Diego, CA Oct 2018 - Apr 2019 Founder/vCISO

Consulting company that offered the following services:

- Virtual CISO (vCISO)
- Enterprise GRC program creation/management
- Project/program management
- Federal technical proposal authoring

- Lead engineering team creating cloud-based Cyber Range used for both commercial and military offensive and defensive training, security capabilities vetting, and cybersecurity product testing (C#/.NET, Python, Bash)
- Functioned as senior software and security engineer for classified Navy/Army Chemical/Biological/Radiological/Nuclear system and classified Navy/Coast Guard intelligence system. Secured very large codebases using SCA/SAST/DAST tools, manual secure code reviews, threat modeling and vulnerability remediation (C#, VB, Java)
- Managed teams of security engineers providing cybersecurity GRC and security engineering services to Navy programs for RMF compliance. Security SME for service-oriented architectures, cloud computing, virtualization, and cryptography. Authored Navy-wide cybersecurity governance
- Designed and built dynamic security awareness smartphone application for the Department of Homeland Security (Linux/Python, Android/Java)
- Built functional prototypes for next-generation military Command and Control systems (C#/.NET)
- As outsourced CISO
  - o Created custom Secure Software Development Lifecycle for clients
  - Trained software development teams in secure coding practices and SSDLC
  - Created corporate GRC and InfoSec programs as well as performed Incident Response, Insider Threat and APT detection, and mitigation duties
  - Managed GRC program to fast-track Federal NIST 800-171/NIST 800-53 security program and risk management compliance
  - Consulted with international airports to design security programs for NIST CSF compliance with conformance to ISO/IEC 27001
  - Created gap analyses for commercial clients seeking FAR and DFARS corporate security compliance
- Created commercial division: penetration testing, vulnerability assessments, IR/forensics, and risk management.
- Conducted international business development (Europe, Africa, Southeast Asia) for C4I engineering products and services
- Instrumental in expanding company into a local technology and security powerhouse; growth from 11 employees to 185; \$4M annual revenue to \$37M
- Won ~\$250M in contracts including security engineering, Computer Network Attack and Defense, SOA engineering services, and risk assessments of all U.S. Navy networks, systems, and applications
- Instructor for UCSD Rady Business School, training CEO/CIOs by translating security concepts and current issues into business-relevant solutions.
- Assisted Navy programs through cloud cybersecurity and acquisition wickets to transition from traditional to cloud infrastructure

### **Layered Intelligence Corporation**

San Francisco, CA startup

Sep 2004 – Dec 2006 Chief Technology Officer

#### **Project: Millivox.Net**

Managed team developing e-Commerce and collaboration website for the sales and secure distribution of digital content

#### **Project: Data Driven Software Corporation (d2sc.com)**

Created risk mitigation strategies, security policies, Enterprise Architecture standards, technology revitalization plan, and engineering procedures

#### **Project: Layered Global Services**

Developed and ran the division performing managed technology offshoring. Managed software engineering teams around the world including the U.S., the Ukraine, Mexico, Russia, Great Britain, and Argentina.

#### **UFO Communications**

San Francisco, CA startup

Nov 2000 – Aug 2004

**VP of Software Engineering** 

Designed Operations Support System (OSS) that automated the business processes of the telecommunications enterprise

Managed software engineering team that delivered seven releases of the OSS over four years, all on-schedule and under budget

Worked with corporate attorneys to patent OSS processes and algorithms Managed tech due diligence enabling sale to Cogent Communications

### **Shippers Network**

Carlsbad, CA startup

Nov 1999 - Sep 2000

**Chief Technology Officer** 

Designed and managed the engineering team building secure B2B Transportation Exchange and Transport Management System

eHNC (now Fair Isaac Corporation/FICO)

San Diego, CA

Jun 1999 – Nov 1999

**Lead Software Engineer** 

Architected enterprise data integration standard; designed and implemented custom security authentication protocol

Science Applications International Corporation / Global Integrity / Tenth Mountain Systems

San Diego, CA

Dec 1996 – Jun 1999

**Senior Staff Security Engineer** 

Architected, built, and demonstrated the world's first and only anonymous, authenticated security vulnerability, incident, and risk clearinghouse for the U.S. financial services sector (in conjunction with the U.S. Department of the Treasury). This system, called the Financial Services Information Sharing and Analysis Center (FS-ISAC), recently won the award for Excellence in Information Security at the 2013 RSA Conference. www.fsisac.com

Pioneered the first security vulnerability advisory system (REACT Reflector) used to notify customers of security vulnerabilities based upon hardware, software, and architecture profiles

Designed and built a host- and network-based security surveillance system (spyware) which detected and audited usage of certain key media types and reported the activity to remote servers

Core developer in the Secure Electronic Transactions (SET) e-commerce protocol compliance suite

Performed security and system architecture reviews for global financial institutions including some of the largest banks and trading floors in the U.S.

O'Reilly and Associates	Apr 1996 – Dec 1996
Sebastopol, CA	Software Developer, WebSite
	Development Team

Maintained security and website production products

Science Applications International	Jul 1995 – Jun 1996
Corporation	6 W 66 F :
San Diego, CA	Consulting Software Engineer, PacMedNet Project

Pioneered a \$38M global Electronic Health Record system that allowed medical treatment facilities to locate and securely exchange digital medical records and images world-wide

Integrated Computer Management	Feb 1995 – Jul 1995
Solutions	
Dallas, TX	Principal / Consultant

Authored medical informatics software for a national hospital group Created an expert system for a telecommunications company

Science Applications International	Feb 1988 - Feb 1995
Corporation	
San Diego, CA	

- System architect for one of the world's largest medical informatics systems; \$1.6 billion DoD healthcare project for Military Treatment Facilities worldwide
- Held various engineering and management positions throughout my tenure

Digital Equipment Corporation	Jul 1985 - Feb 1988
San Diego, CA	Consulting Systems Manager,
	Software Group

<b>Bit-7 Computer Systems</b>	Aug 1982 – Jul 1985
San Diego, CA	Contract Programmer

# **Training and Certifications**

Certified PCI DSS Qualified Security Assessor (QSA)
Certified Information Systems Security Professional (CISSP), (ISC)2 License 372792

Certificate of Cloud Security Knowledge (CCSK), CSA, Code 400627370396

Agile Scrum Training, CollabNet

Department of Defense Architecture Framework (DODAF) training

November 2016

Amazon AWS Solution Architect training, 2013

BlackHat and DEFCON 2011 - 2019

BlackHat Incident Response (Mandiant) training

BlackHat Advanced WiFi Penetration Testing training

BlackHat Maltego (Social Engineering, Open Source Intelligence) training

BlackHat Exploit Laboratory training (Vulnerability exploit creation)

BlackHat Samurai Web Testing Framework training (web app pentesting)

"Attacking, Defending, and Building SCADA Systems" training, BlackHat 2014

"Assessing and Exploiting Industrial Control Systems with SamuraiSTFU" training, BlackHat 2013

VMWare vSphere/vCenter training

CyberArk (Privileged Access Management) Certified Pre-Sales EngineerSitecore Certified Developer (.NET-based Content Management System; ASP.NET/C# and XSLT)

Negotiation and Leadership, Program on Negotiation (PON), Harvard Law School.

### **Speaking Engagements, Publications, Memberships**

- Author (USD, 4-hour course) Anatomy of a Hack. April 2018
- Speaker (NDIA) Hacking Demonstration, The tactics and views from the hacker's perspective. February 2017
- Speaker (FortneyScott) *The Cybersecurity Challenge: A Roadmap to Assessment and Compliance*. April 2017
- Author (Sentek), Social Engineering Defense Training. Oct 2016
- Panelist (NDIA Gold Coast) Small business cybersecurity; Defense contractor protection of DoD CUI data. August 2016
- Speaker (San Diego Business Services Alliance) *The Latest Cyber Threats from the Hacker Underground*. September 2015
- Speaker (Sentek, Barney&Barney, ESET) Preparing for the Inevitable: Best Practices to Protect Your Company from a Data Breach. June 2015.
- Speaker (San Diego Women in Finance) Cybersecurity Impact to the Bottom Line, October 2014
- Author (San Diego Cyber Center of Excellence) WiFi Security Standard. April 2015
- Panelist (AFCEA C4ISR Conference) Information as Warfare. April 2013
- Author (Defense Systems Magazine) Military looking to DISA for clear direction on security in the cloud. September 2012
- Speaker (KNSD-TV Channel 7/39 broadcast) Sentek High Tech Defense Boosts Economy. April 2010
- Cited, Corporations should follow government's lead on attribution of cyber attacks. The Daily Transcript. February 2010.
- Author, *Don't forget who's behind a cyberattack*. Washington Technology. February 2010.
- Cited, Local Arena Plays Large Role in Protecting Against Enemy Cyber Attacks. San Diego Business Journal. February 2010.
- Cited, Cloud computing has uncertainties, is moving forward. The Daily Transcript. October 2009.
- Cited, Governance, guidance necessary in the cloud. San Diego Daily Transcript. October 2009.

- Co-author, *Defining AFRICOM's mission*. Signal Online (an AFCEA publication). December 2008.
- Author, *Bridging the SOA divide for deployed assets*. Defense Systems. September 2008.
- Author, Supporting the National Anti-terrorism Initiative in the Philippines. May 2008.
- 2008/2009/2010/2011/2012/2013 San Diego Business Journal's Technology Executive of the Year finalist
- 2011/2012/2015 San Diego Magazine's Top Tech Exec Awards finalist
- Member, San Diego CISO Round Table
- Member, Tech San Diego CTO Round Table

### **References and Education**

Available on request